so we can go through anapanasati suit
I'll know which is a maje 118
mindfulness of breathing
it says that one occasion the Buddha was
living in sanity in the Eastern Park and
vigorous mother's place with many
well-known all the disciples Coptic Mina
so those disciples of the others because
we're exhorting instructing junior
because sometimes ten twenty thirty
forty because at the time and those
junior because being exhausted being
instructed sooner or later understood
the noble attainments
then the Buddha said that upon the
competition of Hvar around the full moon
of the 15 to post the day the Buddha was
sitting down in the open surrounded by
the bhikkhus Sangha then the Buddha
having surveyed the completely silent
Sangha Baker's addressed the bhikkhus
I'm resolved upon this path of practice
my mind is resolved upon this path of
practice therefore because make even
more of an effort to reach the unreached
to attain the unattained to realize the
unrealized and because from the
countryside returned to society to see
the Buddha and then the other Baker's
continued to tour exhort junior bhikkhus
10 20 30 40 at a time so on the next
full moon on the full moon night the
Buddha was sitting down in the open
surrounded by Baku Sangha having
completely surveyed the silence angle
because he addressed the bhikkhus
instead because this assembly is free
from chitchat because this assembly is
free from the idle chatter purity has
been established in its essence such as
this Sangha Vickers so that that clearly
indicates that the song of the because
that the Buddha was praising was
basically an area which means there were
no the two Gina's day they would know
that the lowest of them at least had the
right view here in this Sangha of
bhikkhus there are our hands retains
destroyed having come to an end done
what should be done lay down the bird
and reach the cause of peace with the
feather of existence
wasted away liberated by right
understanding such is this song of
bhikkhus because in this song or because
there because with five lower fat fat is
wasted away who will attain parinibbana
once they've been reborn being
of the nature to not return from that
world such is the song of because
because in this angle because there
because with the three feathers wasted
away with greed hatred and delusion
reduced once returned us who having come
to this world once will make an end to
suffering such is this angle because
because in this angle because there
because with the three feathers waste of
the waste three mentor is not of the
nature of the lower realms certain of
having an end in full awakening because
they are such because in this angle
because so so yes the the entire because
hunger there did the Buddha instructed
beforehand that he said may their food
and reach the unreached at the Indian
attain realized the unrealized was an
area Sangha and it's important to note
well we'll see why but it's there were
no they were no pathogen is in that
assembly so for those who were not yet
our hands who still had work to do then
the Buddha decided in this particular
suitor to to instruct on mindfulness of
breathing before he started he listed
all the ways that these beakers who were
not shortened in soda burners can do the
rest of the work that they need to do
and reach the unreached and so on he
said because there because who dwell
practicing the practice of the
development of the four ways to set up
mindfulness the such because in the
Sangha Baker's so in the noble in the
noble Arya Sangha the bhikkhus who
practice satipatthana then because in
this song of because the noble song of
because the bhikkhus who dwell
practising the practice of development
the four right efforts the four
foundations of potency the five
strengths the big practice seven factors
for wakening the big who practice the
Noble Eightfold Path there are such
because in this song of bhikkhus
in this angle because there because
we'll go practice in the practice of
development or loving-kindness
development of compassion development of
gladness development of indifference
good work practicing the practice of the
development of non-beauty a tsuba hood
well practicing the practice of the
development of the perception of
impermanence because they are such
because in this angle because and then
says in this angle bhikkhus that those
who practice the development mindfulness
of breathing
so all these relatively popular or
certainly familiar practices in
contemporary Buddhism are practiced by
those who are not shorted in so two
burners which is which is something that
I said repeated often you need a right
view in order to know what to do as in
in order to know how to practice you
need to understand what the practice is
it's it's just the most obvious
reasoning you can arrive that by
reasoning that you can't do something
unless you know what you're supposed to
do and that's where they will insist on
listening all these people who are there
then none of them that's like pure heart
wood and none of them is shorted and and
like a sort of burner and then these are
the practices that these noble disciples
would do now that doesn't mean that the
person shouldn't keep trying to
understand where these practices are
because through understanding you will
become at least a third abundant but the
problem is that it's certainly in the
contemporary Buddhism the one that you
hear a lot in in the West people believe
it automatically doing these things
there's some sort of technique or some
sort of repetitive method you will
arrive at understanding but they can be
done properly only by those who already
understood it so it's sort of
self-defeating if it's done improperly
so
okay so let's go so he says because in
this angle because there because well
practicing practice of the development
of mindfulness of breathing mindfulness
of breathing will develop made much of
is a great fruit great benefit
mindfulness abrini when develop I'm a
matter of fulfills the four ways to set
up my flow so that's another thing
another contemporary
viol established perception when it
comes to anapanasati is that you don't
open a sati in the form of watching your
nostril similar and you entered the John
automatically you will eventually enter
the jannah have the experience of jhana
through watching Industrials and here it
is the sutra in question dianna
panasonic anapanasati suta and there's
absolutely no mention that whatsoever it
says that by developing the mindfulness
of breathing you develop surprise
mindfulness you develop the four
foundations of mindfulness by developing
the four foundations of mindfulness you
automatically get a jonah know you
developed seven factors of awakening by
developing some factors of awakening you
develop wisdom and liberation you become
an hour hand in some other talks that's
I mentioned the relationship between our
concert in Jannah as in an open society
or many other ways of developing
mindfulness can serve as a basis for you
to attend to the Ender to the theme of
Jannah as the Buddha will describe then on
as the Buddha will describe then on
account of that develop mindfulness on
the basis of breathing or something else
properly develop mindfulness you can
develop theme of jhana
but thinking they're doing a meditation
method of watching your breath
automatically results in Jannah
they're okay much later and it's
certainly not found in the suitors so
then the Buddha carries on developing
what way because made much often what
were his mindfulness of breathing of
much fruit much benefit bhiku has gone
to the forest gone to the root of a tree
gone to an empty dwelling sits down
having crossed leg cross his legs making
his back straight having said that
mindfulness in front we spoke about it
in the first order
talk about mindfulness to the body so
just mindful he breathes in this mindful
he breathes out breathing in long he
understand and breathing in lung
breathing our long he understands I'm
breathing our lock he's not focusing on
what he is doing he's not trying to
attend and catch every moment and see
things arising and passing away he
understands what he's doing he
understands what's occurring and in
order for something in order for you to
understand something you cannot be
absorbed in it forcefully absorbed even
worse trying the pond like like like
like a now trying to catch a fish you
need to understand what's going on means
you already need to start paying
attention to the nature of what's
present nature of your action in this
case nature breathing so he understands
what he's doing he's breathing in long
he understands he's really in long and
so on experiencing the whole body he
through he trains I will breathe in as
one who experiences the whole body again
we mentioned that in the previous talk
it's that body that peripheral
mindfulness the image of the body that
appears that's discerning that in direct
manner within the I think I'll have to
stop saying peripheral mindfulness
because just mindfulness but well I want
to stop saying but I can't because
obviously if I say mindfulness people
will regard that this coming under any
idea of mindfulness that they might have
so the body the imager body that appears
in the peripheral mindfulness the
properly established mindfulness that's
the body that you're trying to
experience without attending it without
making it a foreground without making it
an object and in the same manner that's
how you start calming the determinations
of the body the determinations of that
those peripheral images in the same
manner I will breathe in is one who
experiences joy experiences pleasure
it's all done on that background level
as in the more you listen in the
background you realize how much input
you can have in it
without over attending it without trying
to make it an object of your meditation
but discerning it for what it is so then
it carries on
I will brilliant as one who experiences
the determinations of the mind I will
read of experiences that I will read out
who has one who experiences the
terminations of the mind determinations
of the mind being perception and feeling
and you cannot possibly attend
perception and feeling at the same time
as a meditation object but you can
certainly discern them in the periphery
usually it's the feeling that is discern
in the on the peripheral that's where
the craving is that's where everything
else is so I will breathe in as one who
experiences that mind I will breed out
is the one who experiences that mind he
will enjoy the mind he will compose the
mind he will liberate the mind the mind
being the ultimate negative the ultimate
background the ultimate general the
ultimate the ultimate peripheral
determined by done by that which appears
in front of your perception by the
feeling that experience of those two
things that are simultaneously present
in itself that experience is the mind
and you cannot possibly attend to that
because they were required to step
outside of that mind and then look at it
as an object but you can certainly
discern its outlines and then discern
its signs chitlin emitter and there is
all in that peripheral that we talk
about very often so developed in this
way because made much of it in this way
mindfulness of breathing is a great food
great benefit and then it says so in
what way because made much of in what
way does mindfulness of breathing
fulfill the four ways to set up
mindfulness for satipatthana bhikkhus on
whatever occasion a bhikkhu breathing in
long understands I'm breathing in longer
breathing how long and it stands in
breathing out long brilliant short
understands I'm breathing in short or
breathing out short understands I'm
breathing out short for trains I will
breathe in breathing is the one who
experiences the whole body is the one
who discerns the whole body I will
breathe out is the one who
his whole body or trains I will breed
out calming the body determinations how
we breathe out common determinations of
the body on that occasion the big hood
valves as an observer of body in the
body aren't aware mindful having removed
covetousness and unhappiness in the
world in this way I speak of certain
body within the bodies that is in and
out breathing to the body did you start
is turning peripherally on account of
your mindfulness of in and out breathing
is that which stands for your experience
of the body there we said that before
but it doesn't hurt repeating it so then
he goes further because on whatever
occasion bikal trainings our breathing
is the one who experiences joy reading
breathing out cuz they want to
experience a joy and so on it says that
there in that occasion to be good wells
as an observer of feeling in feelings so
it's it's it's it's it's a simultaneous
presence of feeling within a feeling
ardent aware mindful having remove
covetousness and unhappiness you know
and by the way when we talk about
simultaneous presence it doesn't mean
they're two things simultaneously reason
for a second or two or a moment and you
must catch them means that they endure
on two different levels of generality
like a mood for example you can be in
the same mood for two or three days
while in a more particular level you can
have various sort of fleeting
perceptions or feelings over over lower
kind and and those two domains remain
simultaneously present so if you if you
if you become if your mindfulness gets
established upon the general mood and an
endurance of their general mood you
won't be affected and you will certainly
be mindful automatically of all the
things that arise within that so that's
what it meant he's mindful of body
within the body so if you're mindful or
feeling within the feeling or feeling in
the feeling so when a person is mindful
of the the peripheral image of the body
that they had the body there
in the world any particular attention
given to the body that appears as an
object for you that's within that body
and you don't have to be tracing it or
trying to not lose it because that's
automatically in the body that you are
already mindful of like a gatekeeper you
find the gate and then you don't have to
chase the things they go in it you just
stay the gate mindful knowingly that if
you stay the gate you know exactly who
is inside and who goes outside there was
a simile from the zoo this doesn't mean
you stare at the gate like a robot every
second trying to not blink because if
you blink at the gate know just stand
there and you will know who passes
that's it so that's how a monk is
probably mindful feelings in the
feelings of feeling within the feeling
you find the general feeling which will
then automatically include whatever is
particularly felt you're not focusing
hard on a particular feeling and then
trying to discern feeling within that so
because on whatever occasion bigger
trains I would experience it on who
experiences the mind I will read out as
the one who experiences the mind on that
occasion the bhikkhu the bells as an
observer of mind within the mind ardent
aware mindful having removed
covetousness and unhappiness in the
world because for the one who is
forgetful unaware I do not speak of
mindfulness of breathing whatever
occasion Baku trains I will breathe is
breathing is the one who sees in
permanent cessation I will breed out is
the one who sees cessation or trains I
will breathing is the one who sees
letting go
I was breathe out is the one who sees
letting go on that occasion because
Wells is an observer a phenomenon in
phenomenon damas in Dhamma ardent aware
mindful having remove covetousness and
happiness of the world that's basically
only discerned the phenomenon of the
peripheral the dam of the peripheral the
nature the peripheral the nature of
mindfulness you automatically see that
anything you attend within that
experience is within that peripheral
those diamonds are already within the
general damage having understood the
general nature of a phenomenon you have
understood any single individual
manifestation of that nature I a
particular phenomenon so developed in
this way because made much in this way
mindfulness of breathing fulfills the
four ways to set up mindfulness he says
because in what way made much of in what
way there's the four ways of setting up
mindfulness fulfill the seven factors of
awakening because whatever occasionally
good grows is an observer aboard in body
art in the were mindful having removed
covetousness and unhappiness in the
world and medication having set up
mindfulness he is not forgetful because
on whatever occasion or because
mindfulness is set up he's not forgetful
on that occasion because my because
mindfulness factor of awakening he's
aroused on that occasion to be could
develop the mindfulness factor of
awakening on that occasion because
mindfulness factor for wakening goes to
fulfillment so again if a person sort of has has
so again if a person sort of has has
trouble understanding what we mean by
mindfulness pay for a mindfulness well
on the phenomenon of forgetfulness you
remember things when you have a composer
present in your mind it's like a general
presence of your mind not when you sort
of focusing on on sight sound smell
taste touches sensations in your body
that does not maintain your non
forgetfulness that actually takes you
the way of being absorbed with the
object which actually makes you forget
everything else so you you want you
don't want to find one point like one
point and that's often translated yeah
you can call it one poorness but there
is a way of becoming one pointed by
focusing so hard on an object of a
perception even sensations bodily
sensations which is just a object of
perception of touch whereby you forget
everything else
sure and sensuality works exactly the
same way when the mind get bent on
having something you pretty much lose
perspective on everything else but then
there is the one point and as the we
talked about which is you find a more
general point like the domain of the
peripheral for example the
background of your experience they then
automatically includes everything else
so it's not a one pointedness then makes
you absorb so you forget everything else
if the one point is that there's nothing
left out everything is included so then
then he goes further that's how the
world mindfulness then the dwelling
mindful in this way he thinks about he
Ponder's over he undergoes an
investigation of a phenomenon I mean
that is pretty self-explanatory you
actually actively make the effort to
think and understand that's the only way
to understanding can come about it with
mindfulness so he may hear the goes an
investigation of that phenomenon with an
understanding because on whatever
occasion be good Welling mindful in this
way thinks about Ponder's over undergoes
an investigation of the phenomena with
an understanding on that occasion the
bhikkhu because the investigation of
phenomena factor of awakening is aroused
time of each chair on that occasion the
bhikkhu develops the investigation of
phenomena factor of awakening therefore
one thinking about pondering over
undergoing an investigation of the
phenomenon understanding active energy
is aroused on that occasion the big was
thinking about pondering over undergoing
an investigation of that phenomena with
an understanding active energies around
on that occasion the biggest energy
factor of awakening is aroused that
energy factor of awakening he goes to
fulfillment for the one with energy
aroused a joy not of the flesh arises
means a joy not of a bodily kind and
what joy is not for bodily kind
it's the joy of knowledge joy of
discernment joy of peace and that's in
the background of that which is your
body because there is no other body
where it could be no other space for it
to be so it's either in the body or it's
in your mindfulness all the body
because of our location because of a
rare occasion there joy arises the body
comes down and then the mind comes down
on that occasion the biggest tranquility
tranquility factor of awakening is
aroused the tranquil body for one who is
happy the mind is composed whatever
occasion for a bigger with the tranquil
body for one who is happy the mind is
composed on that occasion the biggest
composure factor of awakening is around
Somali on that occasion typical develop
the composure factor for awakening and
that composure factor goes the
fulfillment he is the one who looks
improperly at the mind composed in this
way whatever occasion a big who is the
one who looks on properly the mind
composed in this way on dedication the
bhikkhus indifference factor of
awakening is aroused
Pecha on that occasion the pig who
develops the indifference factor for
wakening on that occasion in different
fact the indifference factor goes
fulfillment bhikkhus on whatever
occasion he bik with Wells is an
observer of feeling and feeling my mind
phenomena phenomena ardent aware of mind
for having removed covetousness and
unhappiness in the world in regard to
the world on that occasion having said
that mindfulness he is not forgetful any
goes to repeat
and he said in what way because there's
the seven factors of enlighten of
awakening fulfill wisdom and liberation
here because a big hood develops the
mindfulness factor of awakening
supported by seclusion supported by this
passion supported by cessation resulting
in the relinquishment he develops the
investigation of phenomena factor of the
awakening the energy factor of awakening
the joy factor awakening develop the
tranquility factor of awakening develop
the composure factor for awakening he
develops the indifference factor for
awakening supportive of seclusion
supported by his passion supported by
cessation resulting in relinquishment
developed in this way the same factors
awakening fulfilled the wisdom and
liberation full understanding one
becomes inherent so that that concludes
this episode so time and yeah this audio
can go in conjunction with because it's
a lot of things that they mentioned they
are fully applicable here most notably
obviously that one needs to have the
right view in order to do this practice
correctly and to stop expecting an
automatic result of some sort of
experience confused to be journal coming
out of watching the nostrils of watching
the dabeli or whichever way people do
mindfulness of reading today mindfulness
of breathing is about understanding the
nature of action of reading you could
say it like that it's understanding like
I'm breathing in long I understand I'm
breathing in long I don't to keep
telling to myself that I'm breathing in
long I don't have to keep attending
every every second of death breath why
because of death of that breath because
I understand what I'm doing while I'm
doing it that's the essence of
mindfulness knowing what you think while you're
knowing what you think while you're
doing it means being peripherally aware
of what's directly happening